if the reasoner delights in conflict and strife. Can reason force the reasoner to want less cruelty and waste? RNG: All on its own, the answer is no, but it doesn't take much to switch it to yes. You need two conditions: The first is that reasoners all care about their own well-being. That's one of the passions that has to be present in order for reason to go to work, and it's obviously present in all of us. We all care passionately about our own well-being. The second condition is that reasoners are members of a community of reasoners who can affect one another's well-being, can exchange messages, and comprehend each other's reasoning. And that's certainly true of our gregarious and loquatious species, well endowed with the instinct for language. SP: Well, that sounds good in theory, but has it worked that way in practice? In particular, can it explain a momentous historical development that I spoke about five years ago here at TED? Namely, we seem to be getting more humane. Centuries ago, our ancestors would burn cats alive as a form of popular entertainment. Knights waged constant war on each other by trying to kill as many of each other's peasants as possible. Governments executed people for frivolous reasons, like stealing a cabbage or criticizing the royal garden. The executions were designed to be as prolonged and as painful as possible, like crucifixion, disembowelment, breaking on the wheel. Respectable people kept slaves. For all our flaws, we have abandoned these barbaric practices. RNG: So, do you think it's human nature that's changed? SP: Not exactly. I think we still harbor instincts that can erupt in violence, like greed, tribalism, revenge, dominance, sadism. But we also have instincts that can steer us away, like self-control, empathy, a sense of fairness, what Abraham Lincoln called the better angels of our nature. RNG: So if human nature didn't change, what invigorated those better angels? SP: Well, among other things, our circle of empathy expanded. Years ago, our ancestors would feel the pain only of their family and people in their village. But with the expansion of literacy and travel, people started to sympathize with wider and wider circles, the clan, the tribe, the nation, the race, and perhaps eventually, all of humanity. RNG: Can hard-headed scientists really give so much credit to soft-hearted empathy? SP: They can and do. Neurophysiologists have found neurons in the brain that respond to other people's actions the same way they respond to our own. Empathy emerges early in life, perhaps before the age of one. Books on empathy have become bestsellers, like "The Empathic Civilization" and "The Age of Empathy." RNG: I'm all for empathy. I mean, who isn't? But all on its own, it's a feeble instrument for making moral progress. For one thing, it's innately biased toward blood relations, babies and warm, fuzzy animals. As far as empathy is concerned, ugly outsiders can go to hell. And even our best attempts to work up sympathy for those who are unconnected with us fall miserably short, a sad truth about human nature that was pointed out by Adam Smith. Adam Smith: Let us suppose that the great empire of China was suddenly swallowed up by an earthquake, and let us consider how a man of humanity in Europe would react on receiving intelligence of this dreadful calamity. He would, I imagine, first of all express very strongly his sorrow for the misfortune of that unhappy people. He would make many melancholy reflections upon the precariousness of human life, and when all these humane sentiments had been once fairly expressed, he would pursue his business or his pleasure with the same ease and tranquility as if no such accident had happened. If he was to lose his little finger tomorrow, he would not sleep tonight, but provided he never saw them, he would snore with the most profound security over the ruin of a hundred million of his brethren. SP: But if empathy wasn't enough to make us more humane, what else was there? RNG: Well, you didn't mention what might be one of our most effective better angels: reason. Reason has muscle. It's reason that provides the push to widen that circle of empathy. Every one of the humanitarian developments that you mentioned originated with thinkers who gave reasons for why some practice was indefensible. They demonstrated that the way people treated some particular group of others was logically inconsistent with the way they insisted on being treated themselves. SP: Are you saying that reason can actually change people's minds? Don't people just stick with whatever conviction serves their interests or conforms to the culture that they grew up in? RNG: Here's a fascinating fact about us: Contradictions bother us, at least when we're forced to confront them, which is just another way of saying that we are susceptible to reason. And if you look at the history of moral progress, you can trace a direct pathway from reasoned arguments to changes in the way that we actually feel. Time and again, a thinker would lay out an argument as to why some practice was indefensible, irrational, inconsistent with values already held. Their essay would go viral, get translated into many languages, get debated at pubs and coffee houses and salons, and at dinner parties, and influence leaders, legislators, popular opinion. Eventually their conclusions get absorbed into the common sense of decency, erasing the tracks of the original argument that had gotten us there. Few of us today feel any need to put forth a rigorous philosophical argument as to why slavery is wrong or public hangings or beating children. By now, these things just feel wrong. But just those arguments had to be made, and they were, in centuries past. SP: Are you saying that people needed a step-by-step argument to grasp why something might be a wee bit wrong with burning heretics at the stake? RNG: Oh, they did. Here's the French theologian Sebastian Castellio making the case. Sebastian Castellio: Calvin says that he's certain, and other sects say that they are. Who shall be judge? If the matter is certain, to whom is it so? To Calvin? But then, why does he write so many books about manifest truth? In view of the uncertainty, we must define heretics simply as one with whom we disagree. And if then we are going to kill heretics, the logical outcome will be a war of extermination, since each is sure of himself. SP: Or with hideous punishments like breaking on the wheel? RNG: The prohibition in our constitution of cruel and unusual punishments was a response to a pamphlet circulated in 1764 by the Italian jurist Cesare Beccaria. Cesare Beccaria: As punishments become more cruel, the minds of men, which like fluids always adjust to the level of the objects that surround them, become hardened, and after a hundred years of cruel punishments, breaking on the wheel causes no more fear than imprisonment previously did. For a punishment to achieve its objective, it is only necessary that the harm that it inflicts outweighs the benefit that derives from the crime, and into this calculation ought to be factored the certainty of punishment and the loss of the good that the commission of the crime will produce. Everything beyond this is superfluous, and therefore tyrannical. SP: But surely antiwar movements depended on mass demonstrations and catchy tunes by folk singers and wrenching photographs of the human costs of war. RNG: No doubt, but modern anti-war movements reach back to a long chain of thinkers who had argued as to why we ought to mobilize our emotions against war, such as the father of modernity, Erasmus. Erasmus: The advantages derived from peace diffuse themselves far and wide, and reach great numbers, while in war, if anything turns out happily, the advantage redounds only to a few, and those unworthy of reaping it. One man's safety is owing to the destruction of another. One man's prize is derived from the plunder of another. The cause of rejoicings made by one side is to the other a cause of mourning. Whatever is unfortunate in war, is severely so indeed, and whatever, on the contrary, is called good fortune, is a savage and a cruel good fortune, an ungenerous happiness deriving its existence from another's woe. SP: But everyone knows that the movement to abolish slavery depended on faith and emotion. It was a movement spearheaded by the Quakers, and it only became popular when Harriet Beecher Stowe's novel "Uncle Tom's Cabin" became a bestseller. RNG: But the ball got rolling a century before. John Locke bucked the tide of millennia that had regarded the practice as perfectly natural. He argued that it was inconsistent with the principles of rational government. John Locke: Freedom of men under government is to have a standing rule to live by common to everyone of that society and made by the legislative power erected in it, a liberty to follow my own will in all things where that rule prescribes not, not to be subject to the inconstant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of another man, as freedom of nature is to be under no other restraint but the law of nature. SP: Those words sound familiar. Where have I read them before? Ah, yes. Mary Astell: If absolute sovereignty be not necessary in a state, how comes it to be so in a family? Or if in a family, why not in a state? Since no reason can be alleged for the one that will not hold more strongly for the other, if all men are born free, how is it that all women are born slaves, as they must be if being subjected to the inconstant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of men be the perfect condition of slavery? RNG: That sort of co-option is all in the job description of reason. One movement for the expansion of rights inspires another because the logic is the same, and once that's hammered home, it becomes increasingly uncomfortable to ignore the inconsistency. In the 1960s, the Civil Rights Movement inspired the movements for women's rights, children's rights, gay rights and even animal rights. But fully two centuries before, the Enlightenment thinker Jeremy Bentham had exposed the indefensibility of customary practices such as the cruelty to animals. Jeremy Bentham: The question is not, can they reason, nor can they talk, but can they suffer? RNG: And the persecution of homosexuals. JB: As to any primary mischief, it's evident that it produces no pain in anyone. On the contrary, it produces pleasure. The partners are both willing. If either of them be unwilling, the act is an offense, totally different in its nature of effects. It's a personal injury. It's a kind of rape. As to the any danger exclusive of pain, the danger, if any, much consist in the tendency of the example. But what is the tendency of this example? To dispose others to engage in the same practices. But this practice produces not pain of any kind to anyone. SP: Still, in every case, it took at least a century for the arguments of these great thinkers to trickle down and infiltrate the population as a whole. It kind of makes you wonder about our own time. Are there practices that we engage in where the arguments against them are there for all to see but nonetheless we persist in them? RNG: When our great grandchildren look back at us, will they be as appalled by some of our practices as we are by our slave-owning, heretic-burning, wife-beating, gay-bashing ancestors? SP: I'm sure everyone here could think of an example. RNG: I opt for the mistreatment of animals in factory farms. SP: The imprisonment of nonviolent drug offenders and the toleration of rape in our nation's prisons. RNG: Scrimping on donations to life-saving charities in the developing world. SP: The possession of nuclear weapons. RNG: The appeal to religion to justify the otherwise unjustifiable, such as the ban on contraception. SP: What about religious faith in general? RNG: Eh, I'm not holding my breath. SP: Still, I have become convinced that reason is a better angel that deserves the greatest credit for the moral progress our species has enjoyed and that holds out the greatest hope for continuing moral progress in the future. RNG: And if, our friends, you detect a flaw in this argument, just remember you'll be depending on reason to point it out. Thank you. SP: Thank you. (Applause)
si el razonador disfruta del conflicto y la lucha. ¿Puede la razón forzar al razonador para querer menos crueldad y pérdidas? RNG: Por sí sola, la respuesta es no. Sin embargo, no se requiere mucho para cambiarla a "sí". Necesitas dos condiciones: La primera es que todos los razonadores se preocupen por su propio bienestar. Esa es una de las pasiones que necesita estar presente para que la razón se ponga a trabajar, y obviamente se encuentra presente en cada uno de nosotros. Todos nos preocupamos apasionadamente por nuestro bienestar. La segunda condición es que los razonadores sean miembros de una comunidad que pueda afectar el bienestar del otro, que pueda intercambiar mensajes y comprender el razonamiento del otro. Y eso es ciertamente el caso de nuestra gregaria y locuaz especie, bien dotada con el instinto para el lenguaje. SP: Bueno, eso suena bien en teoría, pero ¿ha funcionado así en la práctica? En particular, ¿puede explicar un acontecimiento histórico trascendental del que hablé hace cinco años aquí en TED? Es decir, parecemos ser cada vez más humanos. Hace siglos, nuestros antepasados quemaban gatos vivos como forma de entretenimiento popular. Los caballeros guerreaban constantemente intentando matar a tantos campesinos como fuese posible. Los gobiernos ejecutaban a la gente por razones tan frívolas como robar una col o criticar el jardín real. Las ejecuciones se diseñaban para ser tan prolongadas y dolorosas como fuese posible, como la crucifixión, el destripamiento o la rueda. Personas respetables tenían esclavos. A pesar de nuestros defectos, hemos abandonado estas prácticas bárbaras. RNG: ¿Crees que es la naturaleza humana lo que ha cambiado? SP: No exactamente. Creo que aún albergamos instintos que pueden estallar en violencia, como la codicia, el tribalismo, la venganza, el dominio o el sadismo. Pero también tenemos instintos que pueden alejarnos, como el autocontrol, la empatía, el sentido de la justicia, lo que Abraham Lincoln llamaba "los mejores ángeles de nuestra naturaleza". RNG: Entonces, si la naturaleza humana no cambió, ¿qué vigorizó a esos "mejores ángeles"? SP: Bueno, entre otras cosas, nuestro círculo de empatía se expandió. Años atrás, nuestros antepasados sentían únicamente el dolor de su familia y de la gente de su pueblo. Pero con la expansión de la alfabetización y los viajes, la gente comenzó a simpatizar con círculos cada vez más amplios: el clan, la tribu, la nación, la raza, y tal vez eventualmente, toda la humanidad RNG: ¿Pueden realmente los científicos cerrados dar tanto crédito a una empatía blanda? SP: Pueden y lo hacen. Los neurofisiólogos han encontrado neuronas en el cerebro que responden a las acciones de otras personas de la misma manera en que responden a las propias. La empatía surge temprano en la vida, quizás antes del primer año de edad. Los libros sobre empatía se han convertido en los más vendidos, como "La Civilización Empática" y "La Edad de la Empatía". RNG: Estoy a favor de la empatía, ¿quién no lo está? Pero por sí sola es un instrumento débil para el progreso moral. Por un lado, se inclina de manera innata hacia las relaciones consanguíneas, los bebés y los animales peludos y cariñosos. Por lo que a la empatía se refiere, los raros feos pueden irse al demonio. E incluso nuestros mejores intentos para desarrollar simpatía por aquellos que no están conectados con nosotros se quedan miserablemente cortos; una triste verdad sobre la naturaleza humana que fue señalada por Adam Smith Adam Smith: Supongamos que al gran imperio de China se lo tragara repentinamente un terremoto, y consideremos cómo reaccionaría un hombre en Europa al enterarse de esta terrible calamidad. Él, imagino, antes que todo expresaría con mucha fuerza su dolor por la desgracia de aquella pobre gente. Haría muchas reflexiones melancólicas sobre la precariedad de la vida humana, y para cuando todos estos sentimientos humanos hayan sido lo suficientemente expresados, continuaría con sus actividades o placeres con la misma facilidad y tranquilidad como si no hubiese existido tal catástrofe. Si él fuese a perder su dedo meñique el día de mañana, seguramente no dormiría en toda la noche; pero como nunca conoció a toda esa gente, roncaría con la más profunda tranquilidad, encima de la ruina de millones de personas. SP: Pero si la empatía no fue suficiente para hacernos más humanos ¿qué más había ahí? RNG: Bien, jamás mencionaste lo que podría ser uno de nuestros más efectivos "mejores ángeles": la razón. La razón tiene fuerza. Es la razón la que proporciona el impulso para ampliar ese círculo de empatía. Cada uno de los desarrollos humanitarios que mencionaste se originaron con los pensadores quienes dieron las razones por las cuáles algunas prácticas eran indefendibles. Ellos demostraron que la forma en que las personas trataban a ciertos grupos de individuos era lógicamente inconsistente con la forma en la que insistían ser tratados ellos mismos. SP: ¿Estás insinuando que la razón puede realmente cambiar la mentalidad de las personas? ¿Acaso la gente no simplemente se aferra a cualquier creencia que sirva a sus intereses o que forme parte de la cultura en la que crecieron? RNG: Aquí hay un hecho fascinante sobre nosotros: Las contradicciones nos molestan, al menos cuando somos forzados a enfrentarlas, lo cual es simplemente otra manera de decir que somos susceptibles a la razón. Y si observas la historia del progreso moral, se puede trazar una ruta directa desde argumentos razonados hasta los cambios en la manera en que realmente sentimos. Una y otra vez, un pensador diseñaría un argumento del por qué alguna práctica era indefensible, irracional, inconsistente con los valores ya arraigados. Su ensayo se volvería viral, se traduciría a varios idiomas, se debatiría en bares, cafeterías, salones de belleza, y en cenas; e influenciaría a líderes, legisladores y a la opinión popular. Finalmente sus conclusiones serían absorbidas por el sentido común de la decencia, borrando las huellas del argumento original que nos había traído hasta allí. Hoy en día pocos de nosotros sienten alguna necesidad por exponer un argumento filosófico riguroso del por qué la esclavitud es mala o los ahorcamientos públicos o golpear a los niños. A estas alturas, estas cosas simplemente no se sienten bien. Sin embargo, esos argumentos tuvieron que haberse hecho, y se hicieron, siglos atrás. SP: ¿Estás diciendo que la gente necesitaba un argumento paso a paso para entender por qué algo podía estar un poquito mal al quemar herejes en la hoguera? RNG: Oh, lo necesitaron. Aquí tenemos al teólogo francés Sebastian Catellio planteando el caso. Sebastian Castellio: Calvino dice que tiene la razón y otras sectas dicen que ellas la tienen. ¿A quién deberíamos juzgar? Si el asunto es cierto, ¿a quién juzgar? ¿A Calvino? Pero entonces, ¿por qué escribe tantos libros sobre manifestar la verdad? En vista de la incertidumbre, debemos definir a los herejes simplemente como alguien con quien no estamos de acuerdo. Y si entonces vamos a matar herejes, el resultado lógico será una guerra de exterminación, puesto que cada quién está seguro de sí mismo. SP: ¿O con castigos terribles como la rueda? RNG: La prohibición en nuestra Constitución de castigos crueles e inusuales fue una respuesta a un panfleto que circulaba en 1764 por el jurista italiano Cesare Beccaria. Cesare Beccaria: Mientras los castigos se vuelven más crueles, las mentes de los hombres, que como fluidos siempre se ajustan al nivel de los objetos que los rodean, se endurecen, y después de cien años de castigos crueles, la rueda no causa más miedo que el encarcelamiento previamente realizado. Para que un castigo alcance su objetivo, solo es necesario que el daño que inflige supere el beneficio del crimen, y dentro de este cálculo debe tenerse en cuenta la certeza del castigo y la pérdida del bien que la comisión del delito producirá. todo más allá de esto es superfluo, y por tanto, tiránico. SP: Pero ciertamente los movimientos contra la guerra dependieron de la manifestación masiva, de melodías pegajosas de cantantes populares y de fotografías desgarradoras de los costos humanos de la guerra. RNG: No hay duda, sin embargo, los movimientos contra la guerra se remontan a una larga cadena de pensadores que habían discutido el porqué debíamos movilizar nuestras emociones en contra de la guerra, tal como el padre de la modernidad, Erasmo. Erasmo: Las ventajas derivadas de la paz se difunden a sí mismas a lo largo y ancho, y alcanzan grandes números, mientras que en la guerra, si algo resulta bien, la ventaja redunda solo en unos cuantos, aquellos indignos de cosecharla. La seguridad de un hombre se debe a la destrucción de otro. El premio de un hombre resulta del saqueo de otro. La causa de regocijo de un lado, es motivo de luto del otro. Lo que sea lamentable en la guerra, es tan grave de hecho, y lo que, en el lado contrario es llamada buena fortuna, se trata de una buena fortuna salvaje y cruel, una felicidad poco generosa que debe su existencia a la aflicción de otros. SP: Pero todo el mundo sabe que el movimiento para abolir la esclavitud dependió de la fe y la emoción. Fue un movimiento encabezado por los cuáqueros, y que solamente llegó a ser popular cuando la novela de Harriet Beecher Stowe "La Cabaña del Tío Tom" se convirtió en éxito de ventas. RNG: Pero este proceso se puso en marcha un siglo atrás. John Locke detuvo los milenios en los que esta práctica era vista como algo perfectamente natural Argumentó que era incongruente con los principios del gobierno racional. John Locke: La libertad de los hombres bajo el gobierno es tener una regla permanente para vivir como iguales en esa sociedad y hacer, por medio del poder legislativo erigido en ella, una libertad para seguir la voluntad propia en todas las cosas donde dicha regla prescribe no ser sujeto de la inconstante, incierta, desconocida y arbitraria voluntad de otro hombre, ya que la libertad de la naturaleza consiste en no estar bajo ninguna restricción salvo la ley de la naturaleza. SP: Esas palabras me suenan familiares. ¿Dónde las he leído antes? Oh, sí. Mary Astell: Si la soberanía absoluta no fuese necesaria en un estado, ¿cómo podría serlo en una familia? O si lo es en una familia, ¿por qué no en un estado? Puesto que ninguna razón puede ser alegada para uno que no sea firmemente llevada a cabo para el otro, si todos los hombres nacen libres, ¿cómo puede ser que todas las mujeres nazcan siendo esclavas, como deben serlo si son sometidas a la inconstante, incierta, desconocida y arbitraria voluntad de los hombres; la condición perfecta de la esclavitud? RNG: Ese tipo de cooptación se incluye completamente en la descripción del trabajo de la razón. Un movimiento a favor de la expansión de los derechos inspira a otro porque la lógica es la misma, y una vez que se ha alcanzado, se vuelve cada vez más incómodo ignorar la inconsistencia. En los años sesenta, el Movimiento por los Derechos Civiles inspiró los movimientos a favor de los derechos de la mujer, los derechos de los niños, los derechos de los homosexuales e incluso los derechos de los animales. Sin embargo, dos siglos atrás, el pensador de la Ilustración Jeremy Bentham había expuesto la total indefensión de prácticas habituales tal como el maltrato a los animales. Jeremy Bentham: La pregunta no es si razonan, tampoco si pueden hablar, la pregunta es ¿pueden sufrir? RNG: Y la persecución de los homosexuales. JB: En cuanto a cualquier daño principal, es evidente que no produce dolor a nadie. Por el lado contrario, produce placer. Los socios están ambos dispuestos. Si alguno de ellos no lo estuviera, el acto sería una ofensa, totalmente diferente en su naturaleza de efectos. Es una lesión personal. Es una especie de violación. En cuanto al peligro exclusivo del dolor, el peligro, si lo hay, consiste básicamente en la tendencia del ejemplo. Pero ¿qué es la tendencia de este ejemplo? Disponer a otros para participar en las mismas prácticas. Pero esta practica no produce dolor de ningún tipo a nadie. SP: Aún así, en cada caso, tomó cuando menos un siglo para que los argumentos de estos grandes pensadores se asentaran e infiltraran a la población como un todo. Esto como que te hace preguntarte acerca de nuestro tiempo. ¿Existen prácticas en las que nos involucramos dónde los argumentos en contra de estas se encuentran ahí para que todos los veamos y sin embargo, persistimos en ellos? RNG: Cuando nuestros bisnietos se vuelvan a observarnos, ¿estarán tan consternados por algunas de nuestras prácticas como lo estamos nosotros con respecto a la posesión de esclavos, la quema de herejes, el maltrato a la mujer y a los homosexuales de nuestros ancestros? SP: Estoy seguro de que todo el mundo podría pensar en un ejemplo. RNG: Opto por el maltrato a los animales en las granjas industriales. SP: El encarcelamiento de delincuentes de drogas no violentos y la tolerancia de la violación en las prisiones de nuestra nación. RNG: El escatimar en las donaciones a las organizaciones benéficas que salvan vidas en los países en desarrollo. SP: La posesión de armas nucleares. RNG: El argumento de la religión para justificar lo que de otra manera sería injustificable,, como la prohibición de loa anticonceptivos. SP: ¿Qué sucede con la fe religiosa en general? RNG: Eh, no metería las manos al fuego. SP: Aún así, me he convencido de que la razón es un mejor ángel que merece el mayor crédito por el progreso moral que nuestra especie ha disfrutado y que encierra la mayor esperanza para continuar con el progreso moral en el futuro. RNG: Y amigos, si detectan alguna falla en este argumento, simplemente recuerden que dependerán de la razón para señalarla. Gracias. SP: Gracias (Aplausos)